Welcome back to A Push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros. Let's get
into it. Welcome to the A PUSH version
of World War I. If you wonder why I have
to preface that by saying a push
version, it's because this war is
technically mostly an aspect of European
history. I mean, the war started in
Europe. It mostly happened in Europe and
it ended in Europe. So, from a US
history perspective, I would personally
love to go in and explain every tiny
little battle and complexity of this
war, but I can't. All I'm going to do
here is give you a little bit of context
and explain the US side of things. So,
basically, by 1914, all these European
powers had a bunch of weapons. They were
all entangled in a bunch of alliances.
And most of all, they were all pretty
full of themselves. After some dude got
assassinated, one country declared war
on another country, which would cause a
big domino reaction because of the
alliances we talked about earlier, which
is why my favorite historical newspaper
has got to be this amazing one from The
Onion. So anyway, this war happens for a
while and by 1916, the war stalemates
into two big battles of trench warfare
at Verdun and the S. But if you're
wondering what the US is doing,
basically nothing is the answer. The US
wanted to maintain neutrality during
this war. However, it still sent ships
full of supplies to its allies. But then
you see two big things happen. First is
Germany's unrestricted submarine warfare
kept sinking ships with Americans on
them. The most famous of this was the
sinking of the Lucatania. Then by 1917
after the sinking started up again,
America got one more push to enter the
war. The Zimmerman telegram. This was an
encrypted message to Mexico from Germany
intercepted by Britain. It basically
tried to get Mexico to declare war on
the US if the US entered the war. So
this plus the constant sinking of
civilian ships caused America to enter
the war in April of 1917. Now I want you
to understand the American soldiers sent
to Europe known as the American
Expeditionary Forces played a relatively
limited role in combat. That being said,
this combined with constant American
supplies allowed the war to tip in favor
of the Allies and eventually Germany
would lose. This war would end with the
Treaty of Versailles and this will
easily be probably one of the most
biggest controversies in world history.
This treaty will basically force all
blame of the war on Germany and cause
them to pay an insane amount of
reparations. The US president at the
time, Woodro Wilson, also wanted to
create a League of Nations to try and
ally to make sure a war like this can
never happen again. However, Wilson will
fail to bring a Republican to the
discussion, which will cause him to lose
Republican support in Congress. And
ironically, despite him coming up with
the idea, Congress will choose for the
US not to join the League of Nations.
And just for numbers sakes here, about
20 million people died in World War I.
And for reference, only about a 100,000
will be from the US. On the screen now
are AP style questions for this topic.
Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.